{"tossups": [{"question": "One painting by this artist depicts a boy carrying a melon talking to an old woman who is cooking eggs. This artist may have included himself in the bottom right of a painting showing an array of lances in the right background as a Dutch soldier extends a key. Francis Bacon painted a series of variants of a portrait by this artist showing the title figure in a rich red cloak and hat. In addition to a portrait of (*) Pope Innocent X, this artist depicted two paintings by Paul Rubens hanging in the background in a work set in Philip IV's palace. This artist painted himself looking at the viewer in a work showing servants attending to the Infanta Margarita. For 10 points, name this Spanish artist of Las Meninas.", "answer": "Diego Velazquez", "subcategory": "Visual Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "During the rule of this king, Oliver St. John [Sinjin] played an important role in the impeachment of Thomas Wentworth. After adding a new Book of Common Prayer, this king fought the Bishop's War against the subsequent rebellion. That event was partially caused by this king's appointment of a new Archbishop of Canterbury, William Laud. This king financed his kingdom using \"ship money\" and (*) \"popish soap\" while  he refused to call Parliament for 11 years during \"personal rule.\" This king lost the Battle of Marston Moor, where his cavalry was led by Prince Rupert. This king was captured at the Battle of Naseby by the New Model Army. For 10 points, name this Stuart king who was executed by Oliver Cromwell after the English Civil War.", "answer": "Charles I of England [prompt on Charles]", "subcategory": "European History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "This woman's father built a statue of Aidos, or modesty, at the site where this woman indicated to him that she would marry her husband. This woman gave birth to Italus with a man who killed this woman's husband using a lance with a stingray spine. Eumachus and Philoetius slew attempted suitors of this woman. Antinous and (*) Eurymachus competed to marry this woman, whose bed was made from a living olive tree and so was unmoveable. This woman instructed suitors to shoot an arrow through a dozen axes. This woman pretended to weave a burial shroud for Laertes which she tore down every night to keep suitors at bay. For 10 points, name this mother of Telemachus and wife of Odysseus.", "answer": "Penelope", "subcategory": "Mythology", "category": "Mythology"}, {"question": "The dislocation of small cations in these materials can create anomalies named for Frenkel. In these materials, the set of points in the reciprocal space that are closer to the origin than any other reciprocal point are known as the first Brillouin zone. These materials are deposited in films in epitaxy. These materials often grow around a \"seed,\" which acts as a nucleation site. The relation (*) n times lambda equals 2d sin theta holds when these materials act as a diffraction grating for incident x-rays, according to Bragg's law. These materials are contrasted with amorphous solids, since they have periodic patterns of unit cells. For 10 points, name these materials that consist of a regular repeating arrangement of atoms.", "answer": "crystal lattice [accept crystalline solids; accept seed crystal; prompt on lattices; prompt on network solids]", "subcategory": "Chemistry", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "In a work by this author, a \"canvas-covered wagon\" is thought to leave a baby before crossing Coton Mais's ferry. In that work by this author, a character was found \"lying in the shadow of the big stone pillar\" as a baby at Valmond\u00e9. One story by this author describes a woman taking her baby from Zandrine before walking out into a field of reeds. In that story by this author, a man burns his wife's possessions but discovers that his mother was a (*) slave. This author wrote of Louise learning that Brently Mallard is dead before he reappears alive in one short story. Another short story by this author of \"The Story of an Hour\" describes Armand and Desir\u00e9e's reactions to the dark skin of Desir\u00e9e's baby. For 10 points, name this Louisianan author of The Awakening", "answer": "Kate Chopin", "subcategory": "Short Fiction", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "One conflict in this state began when Franklin Coleman was not arrested for murdering Charles Dow in a land dispute. Charles Hamilton carried out the Marais des Cygnes massacre in this state. This state's constitution, the Wyandotte Constitution, was accepted after the Leavenworth and Lecompton Constitutions were rejected. Rifles used in this state became known as (*) \"Beecher's Bibles.\" Charles Sumner was caned for delivering a speech called \"The Crime against [this state].\" John Brown attacked settlers in the Pottawatomie Massacre in retaliation for the sack of Lawrence in this state. Guerrillas that fought Missouri's bushwhackers gave this state the nickname of \"jayhawk.\" For 10 points, name this state which was \"bleeding\" in the lead-up to the Civil War.", "answer": "Kansas", "subcategory": "American History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "In humans, part of this organ develops from the first pharyngeal pouch. This organ's stereocilia are arranged by increasing height. Presbycusis is the natural loss of function of this organ. This organ's utricle and saccule contain small calcium carbonate particles and are located behind the oval window. The movement of fluid along three planes allows this organ to sense angular (*) acceleration in its semicircular canals. In this organ, the bending of hair cells changes the frequency of action potentials in the organ of Corti. This organ's tympanic membrane is connected to three small bones, the malleus, incus, and stapes, which are responsible for transmitting vibrations to the cochlea. For 10 points, name this organ that is responsible for balance and hearing.", "answer": "ear [accept inner ear; anti-prompt on cochlea or organ of Corti before mentioned]", "subcategory": "Biology", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "August Wenzinger is most famous for editing an authoritative edition of six works by this composer. This composer, many of whose works are performed from transcriptions by Ferruccio Busoni, wrote a concerto whose second movement only consists of a Phrygian half-cadence, around which the soloist is to improvise. This composer, who frequently collaborated with the librettist Picander, used a (*) Lutheran hymn written by Philipp Nicolai for his \"Wachet Auf.\" A piece by this composer was adapted into Charles Gounod's Ave Maria. A revival of this composer's music began with Felix Mendelssohn's performance of their St. Matthew Passion. For 10 points, name this Baroque composer of The Well-Tempered Clavier and several Brandenburg Concertos.", "answer": "Johann Sebastian Bach [or J. S. Bach; prompt on Bach or Johann Bach]", "subcategory": "Auditory Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "A speaker of a poem in this work contrasts the \"long dream of life\" with the \"short dream of a game\" and ends by saying \"wake up.\" An audio track within this work starts with vinyl static before a person starts running on stone and coughing; that track is called \"11\" and was composed by C418. An update to this game added new features like axolotls. An anonymous (*) astrophysicist wrote a report exonerating high incidences of blaze rod and ender pearl drops by a speedrunner of this game named Dream. This game features a playable character named Steve and has a final goal of defeating the Ender Dragon. For 10 points, name this video game with \"Java\" and \"Bedrock\" editions developed by Mojang.", "answer": "Minecraft"}, {"question": "The narrator of one poem by this author \"armed [himself] against Justice\" and compares life to a \"feast where all hearts opened, and all wines flowed.\" The speaker of a poem by this author was \"indifferent\" to the \"bearer of Flemish wheat or English cottons.\" A section of a poem by this author mentions how the narrator assigned different colors to the vowels. The title object of one poem by this author \"no longer felt myself guided by haulers\" as it moved down (*) \"impassive Rivers.\" One section of a poem by this author contains two Delirium sections, the first of which is an allegory for his relationship with Paul Verlaine. For 10 points, name this French symbolist poet who wrote A Season in Hell and \"The Drunken Boat.\"", "answer": "Arthur Rimbaud", "subcategory": "Poetry", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "This architect designed a memorial with a stainless steel tapestry of the French coast next to 8 stone columns. This architect asked Cooseje van Bruggen and Claus Oldenburg to build a giant binocular sculpture as part of his Chiat/Day building. This architect of the Dwight D. Eisenhower Memorial worked with Vlado Milunic to design a building he initially called (*) \"Fred and Ginger.\" This architect designed a pedestrian bridge that connects Millenium Park in Chicago with the rest of Grant Park. This architect clad a building by the Nervi\u00f3n River in thin titanium plates. This architect of the Dancing House also designed Seattle's Museum of Pop Culture and the Walt Disney Concert Hall. For 10 points, name this Canadian architect who created the Bilbao Guggenheim.", "answer": "Frank Gehry", "subcategory": "Other Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "Swimming feats were twice performed by this politician to demonstrate his health before he announced major plans. In one text explaining this politician's views, he pointed out that \"a revolution is not a dinner party.\" This politician developed the concept of the mass line while his administration developed struggle sessions. Schemes of this politician were criticized in the quote (*) \"I don't care if the cat is black or white, so long as it catches mice.\" This politician advocated expanding the proletariat to include peasants as a cornerstone of his namesake ideology. The Little Red Book was written by this thinker, who also led the Great Leap Forward and the Cultural Revolution. For 10 points, name this communist who established the People's Republic of China.", "answer": "Mao Zedong", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "An author from this country recalls being approached by Janet Suzman to act in a production of Othello in one essay. That author, John Kani, collaborated on a play with another author from this country, in which the title character adopts the pass book and identity of Robert Zwelinzima. At the end of another play by an author from this country, the protagonist writes an English essay about ballroom dancing as a (*) \"world without collisions.\" A character named Morris poses as his brother Zachariah to impress a woman named Ethel Lange in a play set in this country. A servant named Sam is spit on in the face by a character who claims that \"you can't fly kites on rainy days\" named Hally in a play from this country. For 10 points, name this home country of  Athol Fugard.", "answer": "South Africa [the first essay is \"Apartheid and Othello\"]", "subcategory": "Drama", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "The propagator of one type of these systems is given by the Mehler kernel. That system is improved on by the Morse potential. The eigenvalues of the wavefunctions of those systems are described by the Hermite polynomials. When one type of these systems return to equilibrium as quickly as possible, they have a Q factor of one-half and are (*) critically damped. One type of these systems have energy levels at 2n plus 1 times h-bar times angular frequency over two. The potential energy of one type of these systems equals one-half times k times displacement squared. For 10 points, name these systems with a restoring force proportional to the displacement, an example of which is a spring.", "answer": "harmonic oscillators [accept simple harmonic oscillators or quantum harmonic oscillators or SHO or QHO; prompt on oscillator]", "subcategory": "Physics", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "One candidate for office in this city was accused of not living there because of the presence of salmon in his supposed refrigerator. Candidates for one election in this city guessed wildly inaccurate numbers when asked to name the $900,000 median home sales price in one region of this city. Fernando Mateo lost one primary election in this city to the founder of Guardian Angels, (*) Curtis Sliwa. The campaign apparatus of Dianne Morales fell apart in one election in this city. Kathryn Garcia and Maya Wiley both lost a primary election in this city. This city re-implemented ranked choice voting for its 2020 Democratic primary, which featured Andrew Yang. For 10 points, name this city where Eric Adams is the Democratic candidate to replace Bill de Blasio.", "answer": "New York City [accept NYC or the Big Apple]", "subcategory": "Current Events", "category": "Current Events"}, {"question": "The proverb \"money does not stink\" is attributed to this emperor's reinstatement of the tax on urine. While dying of severe diarrhea, this emperor's last words were \"I think I'm becoming a god.\" The general Mucianus helped this man win the Second Battle of Bedriacum. This emperor freed the slave Josephus, who had earlier chronicled the Siege of Yodfat. This man led the invasion of Galilee as part of his victory in the (*) Great Jewish revolt; 11 years later, this man's son had a namesake arch built for him. This man defeated Vitellius, ending the year of the four emperors. This man began construction of the Coliseum, which was completed by his son, Titus. For 10 points, name this emperor who founded the Flavian dynasty.", "answer": "Titus Flavius Vespasianus", "subcategory": "Ancient History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "Two groups of figures in this religion are contrasted as being sweet and cool or violent and hot. This religion compares being possessed by a spirit to a horse being mounted. This religion identifies the ancestral spirits as Ginen. One deity in this religion is often depicted as an old man wearing rags who stands at a crossroad. V\u00e9v\u00e9s drawn on the floor in this religion may represent figures such as (*) Maman Brigitte or her husband Baron Samedi. The supreme deity of this religion is known as Bondye. This religion's priests, who are known as either Oungan or Manbo, use Papa Legba to talk to spirits called Lwa [Loa]. For 10 points, name this syncretic religion practiced in Haiti known for its namesake dolls", "answer": "Haitian Vodou [accept Voodoo]", "subcategory": "Religion", "category": "Religion"}, {"question": "A character in one novel by this author dreams about working in an open-plan office and goes on a trip to Norfolk after Rodney tells her about a \"possible.\" Another novel by this author sees the protagonist defend a character when that character is accused of being a Nazi sympathizer after hosting Herr Ribbentrop at his house. One novel by this author is titled after a Judy Bridgewater song while another features the protagonist attempting to learn the art of (*) bantering to please his American employer Mr. Farraday. One novel by this author features Kathy, Ruth, and Tommy who are clones that are raised at Hailsham to become organ donors. For 10 points, name this author who wrote Never Let Me Go and who wrote about the butler Stevens in The Remains of the Day.", "answer": "Kazuo Ishiguro", "subcategory": "Long Fiction", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "This man was accused of cherry-picking certain ethnic groups, Sicilians and \"Hebrews,\" to support his claim that the children of immigrants were more similar to other Americans physically than to people in their homeland. George Hunt consulted for this man's work leading the Jesup North Pacific Expedition. This man developed a school termed \"historical particularism,\" which he taught to students like Alfred (*) Kroeber. This man popularized a system using linguistics and archeology as two of its \"four fields.\" The Central Eskimo was written after this man's study of native Inuit on Baffin Island. In one work, this man studies the Kwakiutl tribe and their gift-giving feast known as potlatch. For 10 points, name this author of The Mind of Primitive Man, a Columbia professor who taught Margaret Mead.", "answer": "Franz Boas", "subcategory": "Social Science", "category": "Social Science"}, {"question": "It's not height, but this quantity is measured by aneroid wafers. Thickness is proportional to the natural log of the ratio of two values of this quantity, according to the hypsometric equation. Forces caused by differences in this quantity are balanced against the Coriolis force in geostrophic currents. The gap between Hadley cells causes this quantity to be relatively (*) low in a belt along the equator. Changes in this quantity are related to density and little-g by the hydrostatic equation. Winds are caused by gradients in this quantity. Isobars join points with equal levels of this quantity. For 10 points, name this quantity that can be measured in millimeters of mercury or torrs.", "answer": "pressure [accept atmospheric pressure; accept pressure gradient]", "subcategory": "Other Science", "category": "Science"}], "bonuses": []}